<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd">
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Akeeba Release System User's Guide</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname><firstname>Nicholas</firstname><othername>K.</othername><surname>Dionysopoulos</surname></personname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <pubdate>December 2013</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2013</year>

      <holder>Akeeba Ltd</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
      copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled "The GNU Free
      Documentation License".</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <abstract>
      <para>This book covers the use of the <application>Akeeba Release
      System</application> (a.k.a. ARS) download directory for
      <trademark>Joomla!</trademark>-powered web sites.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

  <part xml:id="part1-users-guide">
    <title>User's Guide to Akeeba Release System</title>

    <chapter xml:id="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <section>
        <title>Introducing <application>Akeeba Release
        System</application></title>

        <para>Akeeba Release System (or ARS for short) is a download manager
        component quite different than its competition. It is designed for
        developers who want to disseminate their software products to their
        clients. Even though it can be abused as a generic downloads manager
        we do not recommend this approach and will not provide any kind of
        support for this use case. Its key features are:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Joomla! 2.5 and 3.x ready.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Full support for Amazon S3</emphasis>,
            including the ability to manage (upload, delete, create
            directories) your files stored on S3 from within the
            component</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Bootstrap styling.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Sensible three-level organization of your downloads
            (package, version, files).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The best out-of-the box SEF URLs, without requiring a SEF
            component.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Excellent performance, now better than ever.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Integration with Akeeba Subscriptions, PayPlans and Joomla!
            access control (user groups &amp; viewing access levels) for
            limiting access to downloads only to specific subscribers.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Integration with JoomlaCode.org; you can directly import
            download items from it.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Allows you to add files either stored on any directory under
            your site's root -even a different one per package!- or directly
            link to externally hosted files without revealing their URL to
            your visitors.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Automatic determination of th file size and MD5 and SHA1
            hashes of all files you add to it.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Helps you keep it organized! You can create subdirectories,
            upload, replace and delete files from the component itself.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Automatic item descriptions. Tired of typing the same
            descriptions over and over? Stop typing! ARS can do it for
            you.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Update streams. Offer updates to your software in two
            formats: INI files easily usable by any and all programming
            languages or automatic creation of <emphasis role="bold">Joomla!
            XML extension update streams</emphasis>. That's right! As soon as
            you publish a new version, all your clients using a modern version
            of Joomla! will be able to automatically upgrade to it. No extra
            file creation necessary.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Allows for automatic updates of restricted downloads. You
            can authenticate automatic downloads of restricted access items by
            passing the username and password or a secure Download ID to the
            URL. This is how we allow you to do 1-click live updates of the
            Professional versions of our software.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Automatic RSS and Atom feed creation.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Automatic handling of release notes separately from your
            generic release description.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>All texts are edited using Joomla!'s WYSIWYG editor and
            support content plugins. Need to include an image gallery to your
            description? No problem!</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Latest releases overview for one-stop-shop presentation of
            your newest downloads on a single page.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Download logging like no other. Even the referrer, IP
            address and country (using the free MaxMind GeoLite2 Country
            database) is logged. Know who downloaded when and what.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><trademark>BleedingEdge</trademark> repositories support.
            Just upload files to your server by FTP and ARS will automatically
            create new releases, download items and publish them, while
            refreshing their update stream. In other words, 0-click
            releases.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>GPL v3 software. We value your Freedom of choice and
            transparency in our code.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <important>
          <para>While we provide the component free of charge, we do not
          provide support for free. If you're interested in receiving support
          for ARS please consider an AkeebaBackup.com subscription.</para>
        </important>

        <note>
          <para>This product includes GeoLite data created by MaxMind,
          available from http://www.maxmind.com/.</para>
        </note>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="requirements">
        <title>Server environment requirements</title>

        <para>In order to work, <application>Akeeba Release
        System</application> requires the following server software
        environment:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><trademark>Joomla!</trademark> and PHP version
            compatibilities are detailed in <link
            xlink:href="https://www.akeebabackup.com/compatibility.html"
            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">our Version
            Compatibility matrix</link>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><productname>MySQL</productname> 5.0 or greater.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Minimum 16Mb of <productname>PHP</productname>
            <varname>memory_limit</varname>. More is better.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The hash PHP module should be enabled for trouble-free
            operation.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The cURL PHP module or URL fopen() wrappers must be enabled
            for automatic determination of MD5 and SHA1 hashes of remotely
            stored files and importing files from JoomlaCode.org.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter xml:id="installation-updates-upgrades">
      <title>Installation, updates and upgrades</title>

      <section xml:id="installing">
        <title>Installing Akeeba Release System</title>

        <para>Installing <application>Akeeba Release System</application> is
        no different than installing any other <trademark>Joomla!</trademark>
        extension on your site. You can read the complete instructions for
        installing <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> extensions on the <link
        xlink:href="http://help.joomla.org/content/view/1476/235/"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">official help page</link>.
        Throughout this chapter we assume that you are familiar with these
        instructions and we will try not to duplicate them.</para>

        <note>
          <para>The language (translation) files are NOT installed
          automatically. You can download and install them from our <link
          xlink:href="http://cdn.akeebabackup.com/language/ars/index.html"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">language download
          page</link>. Do note that you will have to install both the
          component and the language packages for the component to
          work.</para>

          <para>As noted on that page, Akeeba Ltd only produces the English
          and Greek language files. All other languages are contributed by
          third parties. If you spot an error please do not contact Akeeba
          Ltd; we will be unable to help you. Instead, please go to the <link
          xlink:href="https://www.transifex.com/projects/p/ars/"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">translation project
          page</link> to find the contact information of the translator.
          Abandoned languages will show the maintainer being our staff member
          "nikosdion". In this case you're out of luck; if you want to fix the
          language package you will need to volunteer to take over the
          translation project for that language.</para>
        </note>

        <section>
          <title>Installing or manually updating the component and language
          files</title>

          <para>Just like with most Joomla! extensions there are two ways to
          install or manually update Akeeba Release System on your
          site:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Upload and install. That's the typical extension
              installation method for Joomla! extensions. It rarely
              fails.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Manual installation. This is the hardest, but virtually
              fail-safe, installation method.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Please note that installing and updating Akeeba Release System
          (and almost all Joomla! extensions) is actually the same thing. If
          you want to update Akeeba Release System please remember that you
          <emphasis role="bold">MUST NOT</emphasis> uninstall it before
          installing the new version! When you uninstall Akeeba Release System
          you will lose all your settings. This is definitely something you do
          not want to happen! Instead, simply install the new version on top
          of the old one. Joomla! will figure out that you are doing an update
          and will treat it as such, automatically.</para>

          <tip>
            <para>If you find that after installing or updating Akeeba Release
            System it is missing some features or doesn't work, please try
            installing the same version a second time, without uninstalling
            the component. The reason is that very few times the Joomla!
            extensions installer infrastructure gets confused and fails to
            copy some files or entire folders. By repeating the installation
            you force it to copy the missing files and folders, solving the
            problem.</para>
          </tip>

          <section xml:id="installing-upload">
            <title>Upload and install.</title>

            <para>You can download the latest installation packages our site's
            <link xlink:href="https://www.akeebabackup.com/download/ars.html"
            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">download page for
            Akeeba Release System</link>. Please note that the latest version
            is always on top. If you have an older version of Joomla! or PHP
            please consult our <link
            xlink:href="https://www.akeebabackup.com/compatibility.html"
            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Compatibility
            page</link> to find the version of Akeeba Release System
            compatible with your Joomla! and PHP versions. In either case
            click on the version you want to download and install.</para>

            <para>Click on the Akeeba Release System item to download the ZIP
            installation package.</para>

            <para>All Akeeba Release System installation packages contain the
            component and all of its associated extensions. Installing it will
            install all of these items automatically. It can also be used to
            upgrade Akeeba Release System; just install it
            <emphasis>without</emphasis> uninstalling the previous
            release.</para>

            <para>In any case, do not extract the ZIP files yet!</para>

            <warning>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Attention Mac OS X users</emphasis>!
              Safari, the default web server provided to you by Apple, is
              automatically extracting the ZIP file into a directory and
              removes the ZIP file. In order to install the extension through
              Joomla!'s extensions installer you must select that directory,
              right-click on it and select Compress to get a ZIP file of its
              contents. This behaviour was changed in Mac OS X Mountain Lion,
              but people upgrading from older versions of Mac OS X (Mac OS X
              Lion and earlier) will witness the old, automatic ZIP
              extraction, behaviour.</para>
            </warning>

            <para>Log in to your site's administrator section. Click on
            <guimenu>Extensions</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Manage</guimenuitem>
            link on the top menu. If you are on Joomla! 3.x please click on
            the <guilabel>Upload Package File</guilabel> tab. Locate the
            <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button next to the <guilabel>Package
            File</guilabel> (Joomla! 2.5, 3.0 and 3.1) or <guilabel>Extension
            package file</guilabel> (Joomla! 3.2 and later) field. Locate the
            installation ZIP file you had previously downloaded and select it.
            Back to the page, click on the <guibutton>Upload &amp;
            Install</guibutton> button. After a short while,
            <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> will tell you that the component
            has been installed.</para>

            <warning>
              <para>Akeeba Release System is a big extension (over 2Mb for the
              Professional release). Some servers do not allow you to upload
              files that big. If this is the case you can try the <link
              linkend="installation-manual">Manual installation</link> or ask
              your host to follow <link
              xlink:href="https://www.akeebabackup.com/documentation/troubleshooter/abinstallation.html"
              xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">our installation
              troubleshooting instructions</link> under "You get an error
              about the package not being uploaded to the server".</para>

              <para>If you have WAMPServer (or any other prepackaged local
              server), please note that its default configuration does not
              allow files over 2Mb to be uploaded. To work around that you
              will need to modify your php.ini and restart the server. On
              WAMPserver left-click on the WAMP icon (the green W), click on
              <guimenu>PHP</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>php.ini</guimenuitem>. Find
              the line beginning with <code>upload_max_filesize</code>. Change
              it so that it reads:</para>

              <programlisting>upload_max_filesize = 6M</programlisting>

              <para>Save this file. Now, left-click on the WAMP icon, click on
              <guimenu>Apache</guimenu>, <guisubmenu>Service</guisubmenu>,
              <guimenuitem>Restart Service</guimenuitem> and you can now
              install the component. Editing the <filename>php.ini</filename>
              file should also work on all other servers, local and live
              alike.</para>
            </warning>

            <para>If the installation did not work, please take a look at
            <link
            xlink:href="https://www.akeebabackup.com/documentation/troubleshooter/abinstallation.html"
            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">our installation
            troubleshooting instructions</link> or try the <link
            linkend="installation-manual">manual installation</link> described
            below.</para>
          </section>

          <section xml:id="installation-manual">
            <title>Manual installation</title>

            <para>Sometimes <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> is unable to
            properly extract ZIP archives due to technical limitations on your
            server. In this case, you can follow a manual installation
            procedure.</para>

            <para>You can download the latest installation packages our site's
            <link xlink:href="https://www.akeebabackup.com/download/ars.html"
            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">download page for
            Akeeba Release System</link>. Please note that the latest version
            is always on top. If you have an older version of Joomla! or PHP
            please consult our <link
            xlink:href="https://www.akeebabackup.com/compatibility.html"
            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Compatibility
            page</link> to find the version of Akeeba Release System
            compatible with your Joomla! and PHP versions. In either case
            click on the version you want to download and install.</para>

            <para>Click on the Akeeba Release System item to download the ZIP
            installation package.</para>

            <para>All Akeeba Release System installation packages contain the
            component and all of its associated extensions. Installing it will
            install all of these items automatically. It can also be used to
            upgrade Akeeba Release System; just install it
            <emphasis>without</emphasis> uninstalling the previous
            release.</para>

            <para>Before doing anything else, you have to extract the
            installation ZIP file in a subdirectory named
            <filename>akeeba</filename> on your local PC. Then, upload the
            entire subdirectory inside your site's temporary directory. At
            this point, there should be a subdirectory named
            <filename>akeeba</filename> inside your site's temporary directory
            which contains all of the ZIP package's files.</para>

            <para>If you are unsure where your site's temporary directory is
            located, you can look it up by going to the <guimenuitem>Global
            Configuration</guimenuitem>, click on the
            <guilabel>Server</guilabel> tab and take a look at the
            <guilabel>Path to Temp-folder</guilabel> setting. The default
            setting is the <filename>tmp</filename> directory under your
            site's root. Rarely, especially on automated installations using
            Fantastico, this might have been assigned the system-wide
            <filename>/tmp</filename> directory. In this case, please consult
            your host for instructions on how to upload files inside this
            directory, or about changing your <trademark>Joomla!</trademark>
            temporary directory back to the default location and making it
            writable.</para>

            <para>Assuming that you are past this uploading step, click on
            <guimenu>Extensions</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Manage</guimenuitem>
            link on the top menu. If you are on Joomla! 3.x please click on
            the <guilabel>Install from Directory</guilabel> tab. Locate the
            <guibutton>Install Directory</guibutton> edit box. It is already
            filled in with the absolute path to your temporary directory, for
            example <filename>/var/www/joomla/tmp</filename>. Please append
            <filename>/akeeba</filename> to it. In our example, it should look
            something like <filename>/var/www/joomla/tmp/akeeba</filename>.
            Then, click on the <guibutton>Install</guibutton> button.</para>

            <para>If you still can't install Akeeba Release System and you are
            receiving messages regarding unwritable directories, inability to
            move files or other similar file system related error messages,
            please consult <link
            xlink:href="https://www.akeebabackup.com/documentation/troubleshooter/abinstallation.html"
            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">our installation
            troubleshooting instructions</link>. If these instructions do not
            help please do not request support from us; we are unlikely to be
            able to help you. These errors come from your site set up and can
            best be resolved by asking your host for assistance or by asking
            other users in the <link xlink:href="http://forum.joomla.org"
            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">official
            <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> forums</link>.</para>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="update">
        <title>Automatic updates</title>

        <bridgehead>Checking for the latest version and upgrading</bridgehead>

        <para>You can easily check for the latest published version of the
        Akeeba Backup component by visiting <link os=""
        xlink:href="http://www.akeebabackup.com/latest"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.akeebabackup.com/latest</link>.
        The page lists the version and release date of the latest Akeeba
        Release System release. You can check it against the data which appear
        on the right-hand pane of your Akeeba Release System Control Panel. If
        your release is out of date, simply click on the Download link to
        download the install package of the latest release to your PC.</para>

        <bridgehead>Updating automatically with the Joomla! extensions update
        feature</bridgehead>

        <para>Akeeba Release System can be updated just like any other Joomla!
        extension, using the Joomla! extensions update feature. Joomla! is
        responsible for finding the updates, downloading them and installing
        them on your server. You can access the extensions update feature in
        two different ways:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>From the icon your Joomla! administrator control panel page.
            On Joomla! 3 you will find the icon in the left-hand sidebar,
            under the <guilabel>Maintenance</guilabel> header. It has an icon
            which looks like an empty star. On Joomla! 2.5 you will find it in
            the main area of the control panel page, under <guilabel>Quick
            Icons</guilabel>. When there are updates found for any of your
            extensions you will see the <guilabel>Updates are
            available</guilabel> message. Clicking on it will get you to the
            Update page of Joomla! Extensions Manager.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>From the top menu of your Joomla! administrator click on
            <guimenu>Extensions</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Extensions
            Manager</guimenuitem>. From that page click on the
            <guilabel>Update</guilabel> tab found in the left-hand sidebar on
            Joomla! 3 and the top navigation bar in Joomla! 2.5. Clicking on
            it will get you to the Update page of Joomla! Extensions
            Manager.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>If you do not see the updates try clicking on the
        <guibutton>Find Updates</guibutton> button in the toolbar. If you do
        not see the updates still you may want to wait up to 24 hours before
        retrying. This has to do with the way the update CDN works and how
        Joomla! caches the update information. Unfortunately we can't do
        anything about it, especially in Joomla! 3 (there is no way to
        forcibly clean the updates cache).</para>

        <para>If there is an update available for Akeeba Release System tick
        the box to the left of its row and then click on the
        <guibutton>Update</guibutton> button in the toolbar. Joomla! will now
        download and install the update.</para>

        <para>If Joomla! cannot download the package, please use one of the
        manual update methods described below. If, however you get an error
        about copying files, folder not found or a cryptic "-1" error please
        follow <link
        xlink:href="https://www.akeebabackup.com/documentation/troubleshooter/abinstallation.html"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">our installation
        troubleshooting instructions</link>.</para>

        <bridgehead>Updating manually</bridgehead>

        <para>As noted in the <link linkend="installing">installation
        section</link>, installing and updating Akeeba Release System is
        actually the same thing. If the automatic update using Joomla!'s
        extensions update feature does not work, please install the update
        manually following the instructions in the <link
        linkend="installing">installation section of this
        documentation</link>.</para>

        <important>
          <para>When installing an update manually you MUST NOT uninstall your
          existing version of Akeeba Release System. Uninstalling Akeeba
          Release System will always remove all your settings. You definitely
          not want that to happen!</para>
        </important>

        <bridgehead>Live update (versions 1.0 up to and including
        2.3.2)</bridgehead>

        <note>
          <para>This method was removed in Akeeba Release System 2.3.3</para>
        </note>

        <para>On older versions of Akeeba Release System there is a different
        update method, if your server supports it. It is called the "Live
        Update" feature. Whenever you visit the Akeeba Release System Control
        Panel, it will automatically check for the existence of an updated
        version and it will notify you. Clicking on the notification allows
        you to perform a live update without further interaction. Do note that
        if your server is protected by a firewall you'll have to enable port
        80 and 443 TCP traffic to www.akeebabackup.com and
        cdn.akeebabackup.com for this feature to work properly.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="requesting-support">
        <title>Requesting support and reporting bugs</title>

        <para>Since July 7th, 2011, support is provided only to subscribers.
        If you already have an active subscription which gives you access to
        the support for Akeeba Release System you can request support for it
        through our site. You will need to log in to our site and go to
        Support, Akeeba Release System and click on the <guibutton>New
        Ticket</guibutton> button. If you can't see the button please use the
        Contact Us page to let us know of the ticket system problem and
        remember to tell us your username.</para>

        <para>If you want to report a bug, please use the Contact Us page of
        our site. You don't need to be a subscriber to report a bug. Please
        note that unsolicited support requests sent through the Contact Us
        page will not be addressed. If you believe you are reporting a bug
        please indicate so in the contact form.</para>

        <important>
          <para>Support cannot be provided over Twitter, Facebook, email,
          Skype, telephone, the official Joomla! forum, our Contact Us page or
          any other method except the Support section on our site. We also
          cannot take bug reports over any other medium except the Contact Us
          page and the Support section on our site. Support is not provided to
          non-subscribers; if you are using the Core version you can request
          support from other users in the official Joomla! forum or any other
          Joomla!-related forum in your country/region. We have to impose
          those restrictions in support to ensure a high level of service and
          quality. Thank you for your understanding.</para>
        </important>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="uninstallation">
        <title>Uninstallation</title>

        <para>You can uninstall the component just like any other Joomla!
        component. In your site's back-end, just go to <guimenuitem>Extensions
        Manager</guimenuitem>, click on <guilabel>Uninstall</guilabel>, select
        Akeeba Release System and click on <guibutton>Uninstall</guibutton>.
        This will completely remove Akeeba Release System including all
        plugins and modules.</para>
      </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter xml:id="using-the-backend">
      <title>Using the back-end</title>

      <para>The bulk of ARS is in its back-end. This is where you will be
      setting up your repositories, update streams, view your log files,
      upload files and more. Since you are going to spend most of your time
      looking at the back-end, we have done our best to streamline your
      administrative experience. Our goal is to have you spend as little time
      as humanly possible while publishing files. Your time is better spent
      creating the files, be it code, documentation, your dissertation, your
      weekly e-magazine or anything which can be downloaded.</para>

      <section xml:id="the-structure-of-a-repo">
        <title>Understanding the structure of a repository</title>

        <para>Akeeba Release System is designed as a dual-repository,
        three-level system. Quite fancy wording and I'm sure you didn't
        understand anything. Let's break it down and understand how an ARS
        repository is structured.</para>

        <para>The repository is logically separated to two sub-repositories.
        By default, they are named "Official Releases" and "Development
        Releases". Their only difference is the way items are added to them.
        In "Official Releases" you have to manually go to the back-end, enter
        an existing "category", create a new "release" and start uploading
        "items" to it, then publish the lot for your site visitors to see and
        download. In "Development Releases" you do not have to use your site's
        back-end. All you need to do is to use FTP to create a new directory,
        which automatically creates and publishes a new "release", and upload
        files, which automatically creates and publishes a new "item". The
        separation is only logical. If you wish to do so, you can display both
        sub-repositories as a single repository.</para>

        <para>The repository follows the standard convention of
        categorization. Each repository can have one or more "categories".
        Each category can have one or more "releases". Each release can have
        one or more "items". The "categories" are the top organization level
        of your data. Usually you have to create one category per software you
        want to publish. If you are not interested in publishing software,
        create one category per general file type. Think of them as article
        Sections.</para>

        <para>Each category has one more "releases". Think of a release as a
        group of files belonging to the same chronological order. Each release
        is supposed to supersede the directly previous release (the one with a
        higher ordering number than itself).</para>

        <para>Finally, "items" are what your visitors download. We chose to
        name them "items" instead of "files" because they can either be
        physical files stored on your server or links to a remote resource
        served from a different web server.</para>

        <bridgehead>Practical example: Software distribution</bridgehead>

        <para>This is the kind of repositories ARS excels at. Create one
        category per software you want to publish. Let's say you produce an
        application named "Kitten Finder" and a Joomla! component named
        "Kitten.me". Each one of them is a category in ARS. Create one release
        per version of the software. For instance, "Kitten Finder" has
        released versions 1.0.b1 (a beta release) and 1.0 stable. Each one of
        the versions is a release in ARS. Each downloadable file is an ARS
        item. For example, you may have an installer of Kitten Finder for
        Windows, another for Linux, a third one for Mac OS X, a PDF with
        instructions and so on. Each file belonging to specific version of the
        application is an item in ARS.</para>

        <para>In order to allow your visitors to browse the entirety of your
        repository, you will have to create a menu item to the full
        repository.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="basic-features">
        <title>Basic: categories, releases, items</title>

        <section xml:id="category-management">
          <title>Category management</title>

          <para>In order to manage the categories in ARS, just click on the
          <guibutton>Categories</guibutton> button on the Control Panel page,
          or the Categories link right below the component's name in any ARS
          page. A standard Joomla! administrator list page appears. Do note
          that the search box below the <guilabel>Title</guilabel> field will
          filter categories based on their title or description.</para>

          <para>You can quickly make a copy of a category by selecting its
          checkbox on the left-hand column and clicking the
          <guibutton>Copy</guibutton> button on the toolbar. The releases and
          items belonging to that category will not be copied along. Deleting
          a category by selecting it and clicking on the
          <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> button will remove all releases and
          items associated with that category. Beware! You will not be asked
          to confirm this choice. Deleting a category is an irreversible
          change. If you are not sure, unpublish instead of removing the
          category. You can edit a category either by clicking on its name in
          the list, or selecting it and clicking on the
          <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button. You can add one or more new
          categories by clicking on the <guibutton>New
          </guibutton>button.</para>

          <bridgehead>Editing or adding a category</bridgehead>

          <para>The category editor page consists of the following
          fields:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Title</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This is the title of the category displayed to your
                site's visitors</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Alias</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This is the alias (slug) appended to the URL pointing to
                that category's page. It's best to keep it short and only use
                lowercase unaccented Latin letters (a-z), numbers (0-9),
                dashes and underscores. Anything else may behave oddly.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Directory Type</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>You have two options. In a <emphasis
                role="bold">Normal</emphasis> directory you have to manually
                create releases and items. In a <emphasis
                role="bold">BleedingEdge</emphasis> directory all
                subdirectories created in the selected <guilabel>Files
                Directory</guilabel> will result into new releases being
                created and published without your intervention. Similarly,
                files uploaded in the subdirectories will be automatically
                turned into items and published.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Files Directory</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This is the path to a directory which contains the files
                to be published in this category's releases. The paths are
                given relative to your site's root. This field is mandatory.
                You can not create a category without assigning it a files
                directory. You can use the same directory in multiple
                releases. You can use directories in completely different base
                folders on each release. If a directory doesn't already exists
                it will not be created, you will see an error message and your
                category won't be created.</para>

                <para>Please note that ARS uses Joomla!'s API to filter
                directories. This limits you to using directories under your
                site's root. If you want to protect your files from direct web
                access, please create a .htaccess file with the following
                content inside your files directory:</para>

                <programlisting>&lt;IfModule !mod_authz_core.c&gt;
Order deny,allow
Deny from all
&lt;/IfModule&gt;
&lt;IfModule mod_authz_core.c&gt;
&lt;RequireAll&gt;
Require all denied
&lt;/RequireAll&gt;
&lt;/IfModule&gt;</programlisting>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Published</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Should it be visible to your users? Set to off to hide
                the category from view.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Access</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The Joomla! access level / view level to apply to the
                release. In Joomla! 1.5 you only have a choice between public,
                registered and special. In Joomla! 1.6 you can create custom
                view levels, effectively choosing which user groups should be
                granted access.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>AMBRA Groups</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>If you have AMBRA.Subscriptions from Dioscouri Design
                installed, you will be presented with a list of subscription
                groups. Tick the boxes on the subscription groups you want to
                be granted access to this category.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Description</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Use the WYSIWYG editor to type in a description to be
                displayed for this category. You can use plugins
                freely.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <para>Please note that if a category is unavailable to a particular
          user, i.e. due to Published, Access or AMBRA Groups settings, the
          user will not see the category listed in the front-end and will be
          unable to access the category, its releases or download its
          items.</para>

          <para>Clicking on the <guibutton>Save &amp; New</guibutton> button
          will save the category and immediately let you create a new
          category.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="release-management">
          <title>Release management</title>

          <important>
            <para>You can edit releases even if the category is unpublished,
            unlike DOCman.</para>
          </important>

          <para>In order to manage the releases in ARS, just click on the
          <guibutton>Releases</guibutton> button on the Control Panel page, or
          the Releases link right below the component's name in any ARS page.
          A standard Joomla! administrator list page appears. Do note that the
          search box below the <guilabel>Title</guilabel> field will filter
          categories based on their title or description.</para>

          <para>You can quickly make a copy of a release by selecting its
          checkbox on the left-hand column and clicking the
          <guibutton>Copy</guibutton> button on the toolbar. The items
          belonging to that release will be copied along. The copied release
          will be unpublished by default and have an ordering of 0. Deleting a
          release by selecting it and clicking on the
          <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> button will remove all items
          associated with that release. Beware! You will not be asked to
          confirm this choice. Deleting a release is an irreversible change.
          If you are not sure, unpublish instead of removing the release. You
          can edit a release either by clicking on its name (the
          <guilabel>Version</guilabel> column) in the list, or selecting it
          and clicking on the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button. You can add
          one or more new releases by clicking on the <guibutton>New
          </guibutton>button. You can edit the category the release is in by
          clicking on the name of the category in the
          <guilabel>Category</guilabel> column.</para>

          <bridgehead>Editing or adding a release</bridgehead>

          <para>The release editor page consists of the following
          fields:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Category</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Choose the category where the release will be placed
                in.</para>

                <tip>
                  <para>If you had filtered the releases list based on a
                  category, that category will be automatically selected in
                  this box! Filter the list, save some time.</para>
                </tip>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Version</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Type in the title of this release. Since ARS is
                optimised for software delivery, we call this field Version,
                but you may type in anything you want, not just
                numbers.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Alias</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This is the alias (slug) appended to the URL pointing to
                that release's page. It's best to keep it short and only use
                lowercase unaccented Latin letters (a-z), numbers (0-9),
                dashes and underscores. Anything else may behave oddly.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Maturity</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>If you are using ARS for software distribution, select
                the maturity level of this release. The possible options are
                Alpha, Beta, Release Candidate and Stable.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Hits</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>How many times the release page has been displayed. You
                can use this field to alter that number. Do note that you do
                not need to change it on copied releases; copies will
                automatically receive a Hits number of zero.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Published</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Should it be visible to your users? Set to off to hide
                the category from view.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Access</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The Joomla! access level / view level to apply to the
                release. In Joomla! 1.5 you only have a choice between public,
                registered and special. In Joomla! 1.6 you can create custom
                view levels, effectively choosing which user groups should be
                granted access.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>AMBRA Groups</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>If you have AMBRA.Subscriptions from Dioscouri Design
                installed, you will be presented with a list of subscription
                groups. Tick the boxes on the subscription groups you want to
                be granted access to this release.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Description</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Use the WYSIWYG editor to type in a description to be
                displayed for this release. You can use plugins freely.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <para>Please note that if a release is unavailable to a particular
          user, i.e. due to Published, Access or AMBRA Groups settings, the
          user will not see the release listed in the front-end and will be
          unable to download its items.</para>

          <para>Clicking on the <guibutton>Save &amp; New</guibutton> button
          will save the release and immediately let you create a new
          category.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="item-management">
          <title>Item management</title>

          <important>
            <para>You can edit items even if the category or release they are
            in is unpublished, unlike DOCman.</para>
          </important>

          <para>In order to manage the items in ARS, just click on the
          <guibutton>Items</guibutton> button on the Control Panel page, or
          the Items link right below the component's name in any ARS page. A
          standard Joomla! administrator list page appears.</para>

          <para>You can quickly make a copy of an item by selecting its
          checkbox on the left-hand column and clicking the
          <guibutton>Copy</guibutton> button on the toolbar. The copied item
          will be unpublished by default and have an ordering of 0. Deleting
          an item is an irreversible change. If you are not sure, unpublish
          instead of removing the item. You can edit an item either by
          clicking on its name (the <guilabel>Title</guilabel> column) in the
          list, or selecting it and clicking on the
          <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button. You can add one or more new
          items by clicking on the <guibutton>New </guibutton>button. You can
          edit the category the item is in by clicking on the name of the
          category in the <guilabel>Category</guilabel> column. You can edit
          the release the item is in by clicking the name of the release in
          the <guilabel>Release</guilabel> column.</para>

          <bridgehead>Editing or adding a release</bridgehead>

          <para>The release editor page consists of the following
          fields:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Release</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Choose the release where the item will be placed
                in.</para>

                <tip>
                  <para>If you had filtered the items list using a specific
                  release, that release will be automatically selected in this
                  field! Filter the list, save some time.</para>
                </tip>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Title</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The title of the item, used to display it to your users.
                If you are using Automatic Descriptions you don't have to fill
                it in.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Alias</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This is the alias (slug) appended to the URL pointing to
                that category's page. It's best to keep it short and only use
                lowercase unaccented Latin letters (a-z), numbers (0-9),
                dashes and underscores. Anything else may behave oddly.</para>

                <tip>
                  <para>Leave it blank. As soon as you select a file or type
                  in a link, ARS will automatically fill it in before your
                  eyes. Didn't I already mention that ARS is designed to
                  <emphasis>save you lots of time</emphasis>? But please note
                  that ARS will also include the extension of the file (e.g.
                  .zip) in the alias. Unless you've modified your .htaccess to
                  redirect all extensions to Joomla!, this might cause 404
                  errors. In this case, just edit the automatic alias,
                  removing the dot.</para>
                </tip>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Type</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>What kind of download is this. <guilabel>File</guilabel>
                items allow your visitors to download files stored on your
                server, the most common case of downloads. However,
                <guilabel>Link</guilabel> items allow you to link to a file or
                even a web page by its URL. You can use it to let your
                visitors download files hosted on external sites (e.g. your
                friend's site, JoomlaCode.org, SourceForge, Amazon S3,
                DropBox, Windows Live SkyDrive, RapidShare, MegaUpload etc) or
                redirect visitors to an external page. Using the Link type
                will not reveal the URL of the external item to your visitors
                until they proceed with downloading the item. Furthermore, all
                download links are marked as no-follow and no-index, so that
                search engines do not reveal the URL to the linked
                file/page.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>File Name</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>If you chose the File type, this displays a drop down of
                files found in the category's Files Directory and all of its
                subdirectories. Yes, that list could be very long, so we are
                cheating: we only show you the files which have not been
                already used in other File items on any category. So, instead
                of having to scroll through a never ending list of files you
                will only see the files you haven't already used. That's what
                we call a clever repository! Oh, yes... As soon as you choose
                a file, the Alias will be filled in if and only if it was
                empty.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>URL</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>If you chose the Link type, type in the full URL to the
                file or web page you want to link to. Oh, yes... As soon as
                you click anywhere outside this field, the Alias will be
                filled in automatically based on the contents of the URL field
                if and only if you had an empty alias.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>File size</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Type in the file size in bytes. Or don't. If you leave
                it empty, ARS will try to determine this automatically. In the
                case of Link items, it will try to download the linked
                file.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>MD5 Signature</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Type in the MD5 hash of the file. Or don't. If you leave
                it empty, ARS will try to determine this automatically. In the
                case of Link items, it will try to download the linked
                file.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>SHA1 Signature</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Type in the SHA1 hash of the file. Or don't. If you
                leave it empty, ARS will try to determine this automatically.
                In the case of Link items, it will try to download the linked
                file.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Hits</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>How many times the item has been downloaded. You can use
                this field to alter that number. Do note that you do not need
                to change it on copied items; copies will automatically
                receive a Hits number of zero.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Published</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Should it be visible to your users? Set to off to hide
                the category from view.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Access</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The Joomla! access level / view level to apply to the
                item. In Joomla! 1.5 you only have a choice between public,
                registered and special. In Joomla! 1.6 you can create custom
                view levels, effectively choosing which user groups should be
                granted access.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>AMBRA Groups</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>If you have AMBRA.Subscriptions from Dioscouri Design
                installed, you will be presented with a list of subscription
                groups. Tick the boxes on the subscription groups you want to
                be granted access to this item.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Description</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Use the WYSIWYG editor to type in a description to be
                displayed for this item. You can use plugins freely.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <para>Please note that if an item is unavailable to a particular
          user, i.e. due to Published, Access or AMBRA Groups settings, the
          user will not see the item listed in the front-end page showing the
          release and will also be unable to download it.</para>

          <para>Clicking on the <guibutton>Save &amp; New</guibutton> button
          will save the item and immediately let you create a new
          category.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="intermediate-features">
        <title>Intermediate: file management, JoomlaCode integration and
        logs</title>

        <section xml:id="uploading-files">
          <title>Uploading and managing files</title>

          <para>ARS comes with an integrated system to handle file uploads,
          manage files and create sub-directories. It is accessible from ARS
          Control Panel page by clicking on the <guibutton>Upload and Manage
          Files</guibutton> button.</para>

          <para>When you launch that feature, it asks you to select a
          category. Select a category from the drop-down. This step is
          required for ARS to know which directory it should operate on.
          Remember that each category is linked with one Files Directory. Upon
          selecting a category, the page reloads with the full
          interface.</para>

          <para>Right below the category selection area you will find two
          panes. The left hand pane contains a list of folders. You can create
          a new folder by typing a name in the box and clicking on the
          <guibutton>New folder</guibutton> button. Do note that the Joomla!
          API will convert dots and spaces to underscores and turn everything
          to lowercase characters. You can click on any directory to go
          "inside" it. The right hand pane contains a list of file. The name
          and size of each file is displayed. Click on the trashcan icon to
          delete the file.</para>

          <warning>
            <para>ARS will not check if the file you delete belongs to an
            active item. It is perfectly possible that you end up deleting a
            file used by an active item, causing problems to users who try to
            download that item.</para>
          </warning>

          <para>The bottom part of the page is the upload form. It uses
          Joomla!'s upload feature. Do note that your file will be uploaded to
          the the directory you are currently viewing.</para>

          <important>
            <para>You can only upload one file at a time</para>
          </important>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="joomlacode-integration">
          <title>JoomlaCode.org integration</title>

          <para>Having primarily developers of free Joomla! extensions in
          mind, we are providing an integration with JoomlaCode.org, the
          official project and file hosting facility of the Joomla! project.
          The idea is that if you produce free Joomla! software you most
          likely want JoomlaCode.org to host your downloads (free bandwidth!)
          and you don't really fancy having to manually copy links from
          JoomlaCode.org to ARS. We have semi-automated this procedure for
          you.</para>

          <para>Start by clicking on the <guibutton>Import from JoomlaCode
          FRS</guibutton> button in ARS Control Panel page. In the new page,
          you will have to select an ARS release where you want to import the
          file links into. Select it from the drop-down.</para>

          <para>In the <guilabel>JoomlaCode project tag</guilabel> text box
          enter the shorthand name of your project in JoomlaCode.org. If you
          are not sure, you can find that out from your JoomlaCode.org URL.
          Visit your project's page and you'll see a URL in your address bar
          similar to <uri>http://joomlacode.org/gf/project/example</uri>. That
          last part of the URL (i.e. <uri>example</uri>) is what you need to
          type in the JoomlaCode project tag text box in ARS. Then press the
          Tab key or click on <guibutton>Get packages</guibutton>.</para>

          <para>A list of JoomlaCode packages appears below. Select the
          package which holds your releases in the <guilabel>Select
          package</guilabel> drop-down list and press the Tab key or click on
          <guibutton>Get Releases</guibutton>.</para>

          <para>A list of JoomlaCode releases appears below. Select the
          release which holds your files in the <guilabel>Select
          release</guilabel> drop-down list and press the Tab key or click on
          <guibutton>Get Files</guibutton>.</para>

          <para>A list of files appears below. Click on each file to create a
          new item linking to it in the selected ARS release. All items are
          unpublished by default. When you are done importing files from
          JoomlaCode, simply click on the Items link just below the toolbar to
          get back to the ARS Items page where you can publish your
          files.</para>

          <tip>
            <para>If you are using the Automatic Descriptions feature, the
            name of the item, its description and all of its fields will be
            automatically populated. This means that all you have to do is to
            publish it and you're done.</para>
          </tip>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="viewing-logs">
          <title>Viewing the logs</title>

          <para>ARS keeps detailed logs of all download attempts of all items.
          In order to view you logs, please click on the <guibutton>Download
          Logs</guibutton> button on the component's Control Panel page. This
          takes you to the log viewer page.</para>

          <para>The top row of the list contains the filters. Below the
          <guilabel>Item</guilabel> column you can find three filters:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Category</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Select a category from the drop-down box. When you
                select a category, the release drop-down will also be filtered
                and show releases belonging to that category.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Release</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Select a release from the drop-down box.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>The search box</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Type in a part of an item's title so as to filter the
                list by it.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <para>Below the <guilabel>User</guilabel> column you will find a
          search box. Type in a part of the user's full name, username or
          email address to filter the list. There are also two search boxes
          below the <guilabel>Referer</guilabel> and <guilabel>IP
          Address</guilabel> columns which work in a similar fashion should
          you need to filter the list by the HTTP referer or IP address
          respectively. Finally, you have <guilabel>Country</guilabel> and
          <guilabel>Authorized</guilabel> drop downs.</para>

          <para>The columns which appear in the list are:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Item</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Displays the item title (top row) and the category and
                release (bottom row) pertaining to this download record</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>User</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Displays the user full name (top row) and username and
                email address (bottom row) of the user who tried to download
                this item. Download attempts by guest (not logged in) users
                are displayed as a single bullet.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Accessed</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The date and time of the download attempt. Do note that
                this is the server local time, which is not necessarily the
                same as your timezone.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Referer</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The HTTP referer set by the user's download client. It
                only makes sense if the download was initiated by a browser.
                This allows you to detect hot-linked files, i.e. people
                linking directly to your download item from their own
                sites.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>IP Address</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The IP address of the user who attempted to download the
                item.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Country</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The country of origin of the particular IP address
                recorded. IP to country conversion is performed using a local
                copy of the (free version of) MaxMind's GeoLite2 Country
                database. This documentation contains instructions on updating
                it.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Authorized</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>If the user was allowed to download the item, it is a
                green check. If the user was denied the download it is marked
                as a white X inside a red circle. Download are denied if the
                category, release or item are unpublished, or if the view
                level / AMBRA group settings of a particular category, release
                or item indicate that a user should be denied access.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <para>You can short by any column by simply clicking on its
          title.</para>

          <note>
            <para>This product includes GeoLite data created by MaxMind,
            available from http://www.maxmind.com/.</para>
          </note>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="advanced-features">
        <title>Advanced: update streams, automatic descriptions, Amazon
        S3</title>

        <para>One of the most distinctive features of ARS is that it is
        designed with software delivery in mind. Two of the most common
        problems in that arena is providing updates to your clients and having
        to type in the same descriptions over and over again. ARS solves both
        problems. It can automatically produce update streams in a generic and
        reusable INI format, or automatically produce Joomla! 1.6 XML update
        streams for use with any Joomla! 1.6 extension. Then, instead of
        having to manually type in the title and description of files, you can
        set up automatic descriptions so that ARS can type in this information
        for you.</para>

        <section xml:id="update-streams">
          <title>Setting up update streams</title>

          <para>ARS comes with integrated update stream provisioning. Update
          streams are, in short, a machine-readable representation of your
          repository. They can be used by remote clients to figure out if
          there is an update available and optionally ask the user to download
          it and install it. ARS can serve two types of update streams:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>INI format</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This is a custom format, designed with portability in
                mind. The update information is rendered as a standard INI
                format text file. The downside of this format is that only the
                latest version is displayed in the stream.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>XML format</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Joomla! 1.6 and later comes with an extension update
                manager. In order for it to work, it requires developers to
                supply update information in a custom XML format. There are
                actually three type of XML files Joomla! 1.6 and later
                understands. The "extensionset" document serves as the master
                update stream. It contains links to one or more repositories,
                one for each extension type Joomla! 1.6 and later understands,
                i.e. components, plugins, modules, libraries, packages,
                templates and files. The second form of an "extensionset"
                document is the master index of extensions of a specific type
                (called "category") known to this server, e.g. a list of
                components. Each item on that list points to an "updates" XML
                document. This third and final XML format contains the history
                of an extension. It tells us the version history, details
                about the extension, links to an information page and, most
                importantly, tells us where to download the extension
                from.</para>

                <para>This is an overly complex system and maintaining such
                files manually can be a drag. ARS handles all three types of
                documents for you, automatically. In order to add updates
                support to your Joomla! 1.6 and later extension, all you have
                to do is to add the following lines just before the closing
                &lt;/install&gt; tag in your extension's manifest XML
                file:</para>

                <programlisting>&lt;updateservers&gt;
    &lt;server type="extension" priority="1"
        name="<replaceable>Whatever you want to call it</replaceable>"&gt;&lt;![CDATA[<replaceable>link_to_your_update_stream_xml</replaceable>]]&gt;&lt;/server&gt;
&lt;/updateservers&gt;
</programlisting>

                <para>The name attribute can be anything you want. Usually it
                should be something like "<replaceable>Name Of
                Extension</replaceable> Updates", e.g. "Akeeba Backup Core
                Updates". The link in the CDATA section is the XML link
                provided by ARS.</para>

                <important>
                  <para>Since Joomla! 1.7.0, you URL must end with
                  <filename>.xml</filename> for Joomla! to be able to use it.
                  This means that the long, non-SEF form of the URL, e.g.
                  <uri>http://www.example.com/index.php?option=com_ars&amp;view=update&amp;task=stream&amp;format=xml&amp;id=1</uri>
                  mentioned in the XML link on the <guilabel>Update
                  Streams</guilabel> page will not work. Just append
                  <uri>&amp;dummy=extension.xml</uri> to it and it will work,
                  e.g.
                  <uri>http://www.example.com/index.php?option=com_ars&amp;view=update&amp;task=stream&amp;format=xml&amp;id=1&amp;dummy=extension.xml</uri>
                  for the example above. ARS will do that automatically for
                  you when generating the Master Joomla! XML Update
                  stream.</para>
                </important>

                <warning>
                  <para>You MUST NOT leave a space or put a newline between
                  the server open/close tag and its contents. Anything between
                  those tags, including newlines and spaces, are considered
                  part of the update URL and will cause problems with
                  Joomla!'s integrated update system.</para>
                </warning>

                <note>
                  <para>When using the master XML stream, not the extension's
                  versions stream, you should use type="collection" instead of
                  type="extension"</para>
                </note>

                <tip>
                  <para>It is not necessary to use CDATA if you escape
                  ampersands (&amp;) to &amp;amp; as per the XML
                  standard.</para>
                </tip>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <para>In order to set up update streams, please click on the
          <guibutton>Update Streams</guibutton> button in ARS Control
          Panel.</para>

          <para>On the very top of the page you will find a link to your
          master Joomla! 1.6 and later update stream (the first type of
          "extensionset" XML document). You can use that link in your Joomla!
          1.6 and later extensions' XML files.</para>

          <para>The grid below is a standard Joomla! administrator table.
          Clicking on a stream name allows you to edit it. The most important
          column is the <guilabel>Links</guilabel> column. It provides direct
          links to the publicly accessible formats of your update
          stream.</para>

          <para>The INI link will take you to the INI format update stream,
          which is necessary for Live Update to work. More information on
          including Live Update in your components can be found in a later
          section of this documentation.</para>

          <para>The XML link will take you to the Joomla! 1.6 and later XML
          "update" document for that stream. This is the XML file you should
          in extension manifest files, inside the CDATA section mentioned
          above.</para>

          <para>The D/L link is a special link which you can use in the
          Joomla! Extension Directory or anywhere you want to provide a direct
          link to the latest version of the item in the update stream. This
          URL will start the download if the latest version of the item
          specified in this update stream.</para>

          <bridgehead>Editing or adding an update stream</bridgehead>

          <para>Editing or adding an update stream will present you with an
          editor page. Please note that update streams look for similarly
          named files (using a pattern) across all releases inside a specific
          category. You are called to provide this relationship in this page.
          The fields you have to fill in are:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Stream Name</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>A name for the update stream. It can be anything you
                want and is only used in the Joomla! 1.6 XML format
                streams.</para>

                <warning>
                  <para>This is what Joomla! will also display in the
                  Extension Name when it lists new available updates.</para>
                </warning>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Alias</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Used to construct the URL in the front-end. Keep it
                short and sweet.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Extension type</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This is used by the Joomla! 1.6 XML format update
                stream. If you don't care about Joomla! 1.6 or it's not a
                Joomla! 1.6 extension, you'd better use "Files".</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Category</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The category where we're going to look for
                updates.</para>

                <note>
                  <para>You can have more than one update streams per
                  category. However, a single update stream can only look
                  inside a single category.</para>
                </note>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Package naming pattern</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>An update stream looks for files following a specific
                naming convention. You have to supply a "shell pattern" in
                here. This is fancy wording for saying that you provide a
                filename and use a single question mark (?) to match any
                single character or a single start (*) to match any number of
                characters. It's what you already use on your operating
                system! Only items whose File or URL field matches this
                pattern will be included in the update stream.</para>

                <para>For instance, all Akeeba Backup Core installation
                packages are named com_akeeba-VERSIONNUMBER-core.zip, where
                only VERSIONNUMBER changes, i.e. com_akeeba-3.1-core.zip,
                com_akeeba-3.1.5-core.zip etc. This leads us to a naming
                pattern of <filename>com_akeeba-*-core.zip</filename> and
                that's what I would use.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Element</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This is required for Joomla! 1.6 update streams. It
                should contain the name of your extension, e.g. com_something,
                mod_something, plg_something etc.</para>

                <para>For example, Akeeba Backup Core installs in the
                com_akeeba directory. This is the element name:
                com_akeeba</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Site area (client_id)</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Since Joomla! 1.7.0, all update streams must indicate
                the site area (frontend or backend) the extension applies to.
                For component, library and file extensions you must always use
                "Backend". For plugins, modules and templates select
                "Frontend" or "Backend" depending on whether your extension
                applies to the frontend or the backend of your clients' sites
                respectively.</para>

                <para>This is only required for XML update streams. If you are
                only interested in providing INI update streams, e.g. for
                desktop software, simply ignore this option.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Folder (for plugins)</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>For all extension types except plugins, leave this
                blank. For plugins, this must be set to the plugin type. For
                example, if you have a system plugin, type in
                <option>system</option> in this box. If you have a content
                plugin, type in <option>content</option> in this box. You get
                the idea! This is the name of the plugins folder's
                subdirectory where the plugin is being installed to.</para>

                <para>This is only required for XML update streams. If you are
                only interested in providing INI update streams, e.g. for
                desktop software, simply ignore this option.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>JED Extension ID</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This is optional and only needs to be entered for
                extensions listed in the Joomla! Extensions Directory (JED).
                This is the numeric ID of your extension as listed in the JED.
                This is used for the Install from Web feature integration. For
                more information please take a look at the Content - Akeeba
                Release System Latest Version plugin which contains the
                plumbing to actually provide the URLs you need to use for the
                (quite convoluted) Install from Web feature.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Published</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Well, I guess you know what this means! Just note that
                unpublished streams result in empty pages</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <section>
            <title>The INI update format</title>

            <para>The INI update format was designed with portability in mind.
            It is a deliberately simple format so that it can be parsed by
            PHP, as well as a plethora of programming languages such as Ruby,
            Python, Delphi, Pascal, C/C++, C#, VB.NET, or even Visual Basic
            for Applications (if you consider <emphasis>that</emphasis> a
            programming language!). A typical stream looks like this:</para>

            <programlisting>; Live Update provision file
software="Foo Bar"
version="1.2.3"
link="http://www.example.com/downloads/foobar-1.2.3.zip.html"
date="2010-10-10"</programlisting>

            <para>The first line is a comment and is always there. It allow
            you to figure out if the rest of the file is a valid INI update
            stream.</para>

            <para>The software key provide the name of the software item. The
            version key provides the latest version published. The link key
            provides a download link to the item linked to that update stream.
            Do note that due to Joomla!'s routing the extension of the file
            might always be .html! <emphasis role="bold">Do not</emphasis>
            trust the extension to tell you about the file type. When you
            initiate the download, ARS will set the correct MIME type in the
            HTTP headers. You should trust that header instead to figure out
            the real file type. Finally, the date key gives you the release
            date of the latest version in YYYY-MM-DD format.</para>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="automatic-descriptions">
          <title>Automatic item descriptions</title>

          <para>Most often than not, when dealing with software distribution,
          you need to provide the same description and title to similarly
          named files. For example, if you have an installable package of your
          software you may want to give short installation instructions and a
          link to the thorough installation guide in its description. Most
          likely, it will also have a standard title, e.g. "com_foobar for
          Joomla! 1.5". Traditionally, this is dealt with by copying the
          release items from one release to the next. However, this is the
          least convenient way to do it, as you have to copy items, edit them
          one by one and change the file or URL they point to. That takes
          time. What's better is to have your download system somehow "know"
          the title and description of each download item. This is even more
          important with zero-click item publishing like what ARS does with
          its BleedingEdge-type repositories. So, ARS does exactly that: it
          knows the title and description of any file, with its Automatic Item
          Descriptions feature.</para>

          <para>Launch this feature by using the <guibutton>Automatic Item
          Descriptions</guibutton> button in ARS Control Panel. You are
          presented with a standard Joomla! administration table. Editing an
          item presents you with an editor form, containing the following
          fields:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Category</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The category where this automatic item description will
                be applied to</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Package name pattern</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The file naming pattern of the files which will be
                handled by this automatic description. For example, if you
                type in <filename>com_foobar-*.zip</filename> all items whose
                File or URL field matches this pattern (e.g.
                com_foobar-1.0.zip, com_foobar-extras-1.0.zip) will be
                assigned the Title and Description provided below if these
                fields are not provided when you create them.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Title</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The title to be applied to download items matching this
                automatic description's pattern rule.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Published</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>If you want to temporarily disable an automatic
                description, set Published to No.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Description</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The description to be applied to download items matching
                this automatic description's pattern rule.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <para>You can use <guibutton>Save &amp; New</guibutton> to
          mass-create many Automatic Item Description records one after the
          other.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="amazons3-integration">
          <title>Amazon S3 integration</title>

          <para>Akeeba Release System fully support Amazon S3 for storing your
          download items and serving them directly from there. It also
          supports Bleeding Edge categories hosted on Amazon S3.</para>

          <para>We chose to integrate Amazon S3 with ARS because it is the
          most reputable and very low cost cloud storage provider. Using S3 to
          store your download items instead of your server's filesystem means
          that you don't consume your server's bandwidth with your downloads.
          Instead, everything is diverted to S3 where bandwidth is generally
          much cheaper than what hosting providers offer. Moreover, your files
          are always privately stored and can not be accessed by unauthorised
          users, even if they successfully guess the correct path to the
          files, something which is much harder to implement on a regular web
          server.</para>

          <bridgehead>Configuring the Amazon S3 integration</bridgehead>

          <para>Before you can use Amazon S3 with ARS, you have to configure
          it. Go to the main page (<guilabel>Control Panel</guilabel>) of the
          component and click on the <guibutton>Parameters</guibutton>
          (Joomla! 1.5) or <guibutton>Options</guibutton> (Joomla! 1.6 and
          later). You will see the Amazon S3 integration area in the
          configuration page. The available options are:</para>

          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Access Key</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This is the "Access Key" you have created in your Amazon
                S3 account page. In order to retrieve it, please go to <link
                xlink:href="http://aws.amazon.com/s3/"
                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://aws.amazon.com/s3/</link>
                and click on <guimenu>Account</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Security
                Credentials</guimenuitem>. In the <guilabel>Access
                Credentials</guilabel> area, click on the <guilabel>Access
                Keys</guilabel> tab. You will see your <guilabel>Access Key
                ID</guilabel> there. Copy it and paste it in the Access Key
                field of ARS' configuration.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Secret Key</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This is the "Secret Key" which corresponds to your
                Amazon S3 Access Key. In the same page as the the Access Key,
                find your Access Key on the list. On its right, you will see a
                link reading <guilabel>Show</guilabel>. Click on it to reveal
                your <guilabel>Secret Access Key</guilabel>. Copy it and paste
                it in the Secret Key configuration field of ARS.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Bucket</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>This is the name of your Amazon S3 bucket. A "bucket"
                can be thought of as a virtual drive living in Amazon's cloud
                where you can store files in. In order to manage your Amazon
                S3 buckets, please visit <link
                xlink:href="https://console.aws.amazon.com/s3/home"
                xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://console.aws.amazon.com/s3/home</link>.
                The list of bucket names appears on the left hand side. If you
                don't have any buckets yet, click on the
                <guibutton>Create</guibutton> button to create one.</para>

                <para>Click on the bucket you want to use with ARS. It becomes
                selected and the right-hand pane loads a list of its contents.
                Above the right-hand pane there is a toolbar. Click on the
                <guilabel>Properties</guilabel> button. A bottom pane opens.
                On the let-hand side, you will see the
                <guilabel>Name</guilabel> field. Copy the name appearing there
                and paste it to ARS' configuration field.</para>

                <important>
                  <para>Bucket names are case sensitive! This means that ABC,
                  abc and Abc are three different bucket names. Be perfectly
                  sure that you copy and paste the bucket name as instructed
                  above to avoid upper/lower-case mismatch which could cause
                  ARS to not be able to use your Amazon S3 bucket.</para>
                </important>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Default permissions</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Amazon S3 has its own set of ACLs for the files created
                in the S3 buckets. If you are going to be offering private
                downloads, we urge you to set this option to
                <option>Private</option>. This will cause all files uploaded
                by ARS to your S3 bucket to be only accessible by your Amazon
                S3 user (and, since you configured the integration, ARS will
                be able to access them too). For more information about Amazon
                S3 ACLs please consult the Amazon S3 documentation.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Timeout for authenticated URLs</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>Since ARS is designed to work with files stored on
                Amazon S3 as "Private", there would be an issue: how could we
                serve those files to the site's visitors? One way would be to
                download the file to your server, then serve it like the other
                file downloads. This would make the downloads dead slow!
                Instead, we use what Amazon calls "authenticated URLs". An
                authenticated URL is a specially crafted URL which allows
                anyone knowing it to access and download the private file it
                references for a limited amount of time. So, ARS creates an
                authenticated URL and redirects the user's browser to it when
                he asks to download the file.</para>

                <para>This ARS configuration option determines for how long
                the authenticated URL will be valid. By default, this is 1
                minute, which is more than ample time to initiate the
                download. However, if your client is using a download manager
                and schedules the download for a later time, the URL will have
                expired before the download manager tries to access it,
                causing the download to fail. If you get grumpy users
                complaining that your downloads don't work, you can increase
                this timeout. We consider that anything over one day is an
                overkill, but it's your option to set it to as high as you
                want, up to a full month.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <bridgehead>Creating categories linked to S3</bridgehead>

          <para>Any ARS category can be instructed to look inside your
          configured S3 bucket instead of your server's filesystem. In the
          <guilabel>Files Directory</guilabel> option of the category you have
          to enter something like <filename>s3://mydirectory</filename> where
          mydirectory is the name of a directory in your S3 bucket. If you
          want to use your bucket's root for this category (not recommended!)
          you can simply enter <filename>s3://</filename> in this
          field.</para>

          <para>From that point, all file operations are performed against the
          S3 bucket instead of your server's filesystem. In fact, you can use
          the <guibutton>Upload and Manage Files</guibutton> button in ARS'
          Control Panel page to upload and delete files in your S3 bucket, or
          create new directories into it. When you are creating items in this
          category, make sure you select "File" from the type drop-down and
          after a few seconds you will see a list of your files stored on
          Amazon S3. And, yes, Amazon S3 integration works with Normal and
          Bleeding Edge categories alike!</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter xml:id="creating-frontend-items">
      <title>Creating front-end items</title>

      <para>A repository system is worth nothing if it can't be accessed from
      your site's visitors. ARS comes with ten different public layouts so
      that you can always present it the way you want. On top of that it uses
      Chameleon skinning. This is a technique originally developed by Stian
      Didriksen and used in the NinjaBoard forum component. Instead of
      providing you a huge CSS file you have to customize to make the
      component look good, Chameleon skinning uses module chrome to render its
      output. In other words, pieces of the pages generated by ARS look like
      Joomla! modules. Leveraging this technique allows you to quickly "skin"
      ARS to look beautiful on your site in less than 5 minutes, without
      writing a single line of CSS.</para>

      <section xml:id="repository-views">
        <title>Creating repository views</title>

        <para>When creating a new menu item, select the <guilabel>Akeeba
        Release System</guilabel> menu type. In the expanded layout tree you
        can select one of the following options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>BleedingEdge releases</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>It only shows the BleedingEdge categories, most commonly
              used to serve developer releases / nightly builds.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Normal releases</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>It only shows the categories of the "Normal" type.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Entire repository</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Shows both kinds of categories.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>You have the following <guilabel>Parameters
        (Basic)</guilabel>:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Categories grouping</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Set to Normal first in order to show categories of the
              Normal type on top. Set to None to show all categories based on
              the ordering you specify below.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Category ordering</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Choose the ordering you'd like to apply to the categories
              listing</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Releases ordering</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>When a user clicks on a category, it defines the ordering
              to be applied to the release of that category</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Items ordering</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>When a user clicks on a release, it defines the ordering
              to be applied to the items of that release</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>In the <guilabel>Parameters Advanced</guilabel> you have the
        following options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show pagination</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Should we show the pagination (links to the individual
              pages) on the bottom of the page?</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Pagination results</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Should we show the pagination results (page X of Y) on the
              bottom of the page?</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show a feed link</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>If enabled, the page will include links to the RSS and
              Atom feeds. This is useful to provide push updates to your
              clients.</para>

              <tip>
                <para>If you want to let people know whenever you release new
                software by email, you can use Feedburner. First, copy the RSS
                feed URL and then disable the feed links. Go to FeedBurner,
                burn a new feed with that RSS feed and choose to enable email
                subscriptions to the feed. Provide a link to the subscription
                page or a subscription form in a module on the repository page
                for your visitors to subscribe. Super easy and very
                efficient!</para>
              </tip>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="latest-releases-views">
        <title>Creating a "Latest Releases" view</title>

        <para>The "Latest Releases" view is a single page overview showing all
        the categories, their latest releases and the download items on each
        one of then. You can view a live (and working!) demo on
        https://www.akeebabackup.com/latest. When creating a new menu item,
        select the <guilabel>Akeeba Release System</guilabel> menu type. In
        the expanded layout tree select <guilabel>Latest
        Releases</guilabel>.</para>

        <para>You have the following <guilabel>Parameters
        (Basic)</guilabel>:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Category ordering</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Choose the ordering you'd like to apply to the categories
              listing</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Releases ordering</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>When a user clicks on a category, it defines the ordering
              to be applied to the release of that category</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Items ordering</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>When a user clicks on a release, it defines the ordering
              to be applied to the items of that release</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>In the <guilabel>Parameters Advanced</guilabel> you have the
        following options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show pagination</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Should we show the pagination (links to the individual
              pages) on the bottom of the page?</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Pagination results</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Should we show the pagination results (page X of Y) on the
              bottom of the page?</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show a feed link</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>If enabled, the page will include links to the RSS and
              Atom feeds. This is useful to provide push updates to your
              clients.</para>

              <tip>
                <para>If you want to let people know whenever you release new
                software by email, you can use Feedburner. First, copy the RSS
                feed URL and then disable the feed links. Go to FeedBurner,
                burn a new feed with that RSS feed and choose to enable email
                subscriptions to the feed. Provide a link to the subscription
                page or a subscription form in a module on the repository page
                for your visitors to subscribe. Super easy and very
                efficient!</para>
              </tip>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="category-views">
        <title>Creating category views</title>

        <para>When creating a new menu item, select the <guilabel>Akeeba
        Release System</guilabel> menu type. In the expanded layout tree you
        can select <guilabel>Category View</guilabel>.</para>

        <para>You have the following <guilabel>Parameters
        (Basic)</guilabel>:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Select category</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Choose the category you'd like to list</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Releases ordering</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>It defines the ordering to be applied to the release of
              that category</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Items ordering</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>When a user clicks on a release, it defines the ordering
              to be applied to the items of that release</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>In the <guilabel>Parameters Advanced</guilabel> you have the
        following options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show pagination</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Should we show the pagination (links to the individual
              pages) on the bottom of the page?</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Pagination results</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Should we show the pagination results (page X of Y) on the
              bottom of the page?</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show a feed link</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>If enabled, the page will include links to the RSS and
              Atom feeds. This is useful to provide push updates to your
              clients.</para>

              <tip>
                <para>If you want to let people know whenever you release new
                versions of your software by email, you can use Feedburner.
                First, copy the RSS feed URL and then disable the feed links.
                Go to FeedBurner, burn a new feed with that RSS feed and
                choose to enable email subscriptions to the feed. Provide a
                link to the subscription page or a subscription form in a
                module on the repository page for your visitors to subscribe.
                Super easy and very efficient!</para>
              </tip>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="release-views">
        <title>Creating release views</title>

        <para>When creating a new menu item, select the <guilabel>Akeeba
        Release System</guilabel> menu type. In the expanded layout tree you
        can select <guilabel>Release View</guilabel>.</para>

        <para>You have the following <guilabel>Parameters
        (Basic)</guilabel>:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Select release</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Choose the release you'd like to list</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Items ordering</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>It defines the ordering to be applied to the items of that
              release</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>In the <guilabel>Parameters Advanced</guilabel> you have the
        following options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show pagination</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Should we show the pagination (links to the individual
              pages) on the bottom of the page?</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Pagination results</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Should we show the pagination results (page X of Y) on the
              bottom of the page?</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show a feed link</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>If enabled, the page will include links to the RSS and
              Atom feeds. This is useful to provide push updates to your
              clients.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="make-it-look-beautiful">
        <title>Making it look beautiful (component options)</title>

        <bridgehead>Bleeding Edge options</bridgehead>

        <para>By default, releases in Bleeding Edge categories automatically
        generate a CHANGELOG and save it in the release notes based on the
        changed lines between the CHANGELOG files found in a release which is
        about to be published and the previously published release in the same
        Bleeding Edge category. You can customise how that works with
        parameters found in the component Options page.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Generate changelog for Bleeding Edge releases</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>When it's turned off the CHANGELOG will not be created and
              saved in the release notes.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Colorise Changelog</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>By default ARS adds some class names to each CHANGELOG
              line to allow color-coding each line based on whether it's an
              addition, deletion, modification, bug fix and so on. When this
              option is disabled these classes are not added. This could
              allow, for example, a content plugin to perform its own custom
              formatting of the CHANGELOG.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <bridgehead>Front-end display options</bridgehead>

        <para>If you want to fully customise the display of the component you
        have to do <link
        xlink:href="http://docs.joomla.org/How_to_override_the_output_from_the_Joomla!_core"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">template overrides</link>.
        But for simple stuff, like defining if the MD5 sum should be shown or
        to define what the users see when they are not allowed to access an
        item there are much simpler and more user friendly options.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>No Access URL</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>When a user tries to access a category, release or item
              that he has no access to he normally gets a standard-issue
              Joomla! 403 Forbidden page. Not really user-friendly. Sometimes
              it's best to direct them to a page explaining why they have no
              access and give them instructions to subscribe to your services.
              That's what this option does. Give the URL where the visitors
              will be directed when they try to access a category, release or
              item they have no access to.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show file size</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Should the release display the file size for each
              item?</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show MD5</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Should the release display the MD5 sum for each
              item?</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show SHA1</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Should the release display the SHA1 sum for each
              item?</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show environments (compatibility)</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Should the release display the environment (compatibility)
              badges for each item?</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para><bridgehead>Direct Link Options</bridgehead>ARS is excellent for
        distributing subscription-based software. However this requires the
        users to log in to your site, download the file to their device /
        computer and then use it. This is just fine when your users are using
        a full-blown computer, e.g. a desktop or a laptop. This doesn't really
        work when they are using a mobile device like a smartphone or a
        tablet. In those cases it would be much better if you could just give
        them a "pre-signed" URL which allows them to download the software
        directly, without having to log in. If you are in the business of
        distributing Joomla! extensions (like us) this direct link can be used
        with Joomla!'s "Install from URL" feature to allow your users to
        easily install the extension on their site.</para>

        <para>And that's exactly what the Direct Link is: a link (URL) which
        can be used with Joomla!'s "Install from URL" feature to install
        subscription-based extensions. Of course you may find more creative
        uses for it!</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Show Direct Link</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>When it's enabled a "Direct Link" link will be shown next
              to the regular download link of each item.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Direct Link extensions</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>A comma-separated list of file extensions for which we
              should display Direct Link links. Do not include the dots. Do
              not leave spaces between the comma and the extension. We
              recommend using <option>zip,tar,tar.gz</option> in here.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Direct Link description</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The tooltip for the Direct Link links. It's a good idea to
              use this to explain to your users what the Direct Link is all
              about.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter xml:id="advanced-uses">
      <title>Advanced uses</title>

      <para>ARS was designed with advanced users, professional site builders
      and, most importantly, developers in mind. We offer some features never
      seen before in a download repository, like 0-click publishing, country
      logging and an easy way to provide 1-click updates to your own
      extensions!</para>

      <section xml:id="content-plugins">
        <title>The content plugins</title>

        <para>Akeeba Release System comes bundled with content plugins which
        make your life easier. Content plugins can be used in all areas of
        Joomla! and its components which support content preparation, such as
        articles, category descriptions, Custom HTML modules, K2, Zoo, Akeeba
        Release System itself (the descriptions support content plugins),
        Akeeba Subscriptions and so on.</para>

        <section xml:id="content-plugins-dlid">
          <title>The Download ID plugin</title>

          <para>Shown in the plugin manager as: <guilabel>Content - Download
          ID</guilabel></para>

          <note>
            <para>This plugin only appeals to developers. If you are not a
            developer you don't need and you are not supposed to understand
            this part of the documentation. If you are not a developer, just
            disable this plugin.</para>
          </note>

          <para>If you want to provide updates to registered users /
          subscribers you will find out that the download URL in the XML and
          INI update streams results in a 403 Forbidden error. This is normal.
          These downloads are only available to registered users, but
          accessing the URL directly, from Joomla!'s perspective, is a guest
          (non logged in) visitor trying to access the URL. This of course
          results in a 403 Forbidden error and begs the question: how do you
          authenticate users?</para>

          <para>The answer to that question is the Download ID. The Download
          ID is a unique, random hash which uniquely identifies the user to
          ARS. Appending the download URL with the
          dlid=<replaceable>download_id</replaceable> query string parameter
          will allow ARS to authenticate the user and, if they have access to
          the download, proceed with the download.</para>

          <para>You need to be able to communicate this Download ID to your
          users. This is where this plugin comes in use. Just enter
          <programlisting>{dlid}</programlisting>in an article, Custom HTML
          module or anywhere else where content plugins are supported. It will
          be replaced with the download ID of the current user, e.g.
          abcdef01234567890abcdef01234567890, or a blank string if the user is
          a guest.</para>

          <important>
            <para>Just because a Download ID is displayed for a user it
            doesn't mean that the user has access to any downloads. Think of
            the Download ID as a combined, abbreviated form of a username and
            a password.</para>
          </important>

          <warning>
            <para>Since ARS 3 a Download ID can only change when the user
            clicks on the Reset button in the Download ID page of ARS. On
            older versions of ARS the Download ID would change whenever your
            users changed or resets their password, <emphasis>even if the new
            password is the same as the old one</emphasis>.</para>
          </warning>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="content-plugins-latest">
          <title>The Latest Release plugin</title>

          <para>Shown in the plugin manager as: <guilabel>Content - Akeeba
          Release System Latest Releases</guilabel></para>

          <para>Many times you want to include the latest published version
          number of a specific category in your content articles. Surely, you
          can just type it out. This works perfectly when you only do that in
          one or two places, provided that you remember to edit this
          information every single time you make a new release. However, after
          a while, it becomes too cumbersome. Especially when this information
          is present in more than two places and/or you have more than a
          handful of categories. This is where this plugin comes in to save
          your day. It allows you to automatically display the version number
          and URL of the latest release. Moreover, it allows you to link
          directly to specific items in the latest release of a
          category.</para>

          <bridgehead>Showing the latest release version number</bridgehead>

          <para>Syntax:</para>

          <programlisting>{arslatest <emphasis role="bold">release</emphasis> <replaceable>Category Name</replaceable>}</programlisting>

          <para>where Category Name is the name of the Akeeba Release System
          category (not the alias, the title). This will return the latest
          release's version number, e.g. 1.0.</para>

          <bridgehead>Creating links to the latest release</bridgehead>

          <para>Syntax:</para>

          <programlisting>{arslatest <emphasis role="bold">release_link</emphasis> <replaceable>Category Name</replaceable>}</programlisting>

          <para>where Category Name is the name of the Akeeba Release System
          category (not the alias, the title). This will return the URL to
          latest release's version number, e.g. 1.0. Please note that this is
          the URL, not a link! If you want to use it as a link you will need
          something like this:</para>

          <programlisting>&lt;a href="{arslatest <emphasis role="bold">release_link</emphasis> <replaceable>Category Name</replaceable>}"&gt;Your link text&lt;/a&gt;</programlisting>

          <para>You can combine it with the version number syntax for
          something like this:</para>

          <programlisting>&lt;a href="{arslatest <emphasis role="bold">release_link</emphasis> <replaceable>Category Name</replaceable>}"&gt;My category,
version {arslatest <emphasis role="bold">release</emphasis> <replaceable>Category Name</replaceable>}&lt;/a&gt;</programlisting>

          <bridgehead>Creating links to specific items in the latest
          release</bridgehead>

          <para>Syntax:</para>

          <programlisting>{arslatest <emphasis role="bold">item_link</emphasis> <emphasis
              role="bold">"</emphasis><replaceable>pattern</replaceable><emphasis
              role="bold">"</emphasis> <replaceable>Category Name</replaceable>}</programlisting>

          <para>where Category Name is the name of the Akeeba Release System
          category and pattern is a file naming pattern, enclosed in double
          quotes. For example, in order to create a link to a download item
          for a file whose names begins with com_foobar and ends in .zip in
          the Foobar category you would have to do:</para>

          <programlisting>{arslatest item_link 'com_foobar*.zip' Foobar}</programlisting>

          <para>Please note that this is the URL, not a link! If you want to
          use it as a link you will need something like this:</para>

          <para><programlisting>&lt;a href="{arslatest item_link 'com_foobar*.zip' Foobar}"&gt;Download latest version&lt;/a&gt;</programlisting>or
          combine it with the version number syntax to have something even
          more useful:</para>

          <para><programlisting>&lt;a href="{arslatest item_link 'com_foobar*.zip' Foobar}"&gt;Download
Foobar version {arslatest release Foobar}&lt;/a&gt;</programlisting></para>

          <bridgehead>Creating links to specific items by means of the update
          stream ID</bridgehead>

          <para>Syntax:</para>

          <programlisting>{arslatest <emphasis role="bold">stream_link</emphasis> <replaceable>Stream ID</replaceable>}</programlisting>

          <para>where Stream ID is the numeric ID of an update stream, as
          shown in the leftmost column of the Update Streams page.</para>

          <para>Please note that this is the URL, not a link! If you want to
          use it as a link you will need something like this:</para>

          <para><programlisting>&lt;a href="{arslatest stream_link 123}"&gt;Download latest version&lt;/a&gt;</programlisting>or
          combine it with the version number syntax to have something even
          more useful:</para>

          <para><programlisting>&lt;a href="{arslatest stream_link 123}"&gt;Download
Foobar version {arslatest release Foobar}&lt;/a&gt;</programlisting></para>

          <bridgehead>Creating links for the Install from Web
          feature</bridgehead>

          <important>
            <para>The <guilabel>System - Akeeba Release System integration
            with Install from Web</guilabel> plugin must be published for this
            feature to work.</para>
          </important>

          <para>This is used to provide integration with the Install from Web
          feature introduced in Joomla! 3.2. When a user clicks the Install or
          Buy &amp; Install button in the "Install from Web" page on their
          site, the Joomla! Extensions Directory page will send your site the
          JED extension ID and a link to the user's site. Our plugin will
          generate a link that takes your user back to their site, with the
          installation URL for the latest version already filled in for them.
          Please note that you MUST have enabled the system plugin mentioned
          in the box above, otherwise this feature WILL NOT WORK AT
          ALL!</para>

          <para>Syntax:</para>

          <programlisting>{arslatest <emphasis role="bold">installfromweb</emphasis> <replaceable>Stream ID</replaceable>}</programlisting>

          <para>where Stream ID is the numeric ID of an update stream, as
          shown in the leftmost column of the Update Streams page. The Stream
          ID is not used if a JED extension ID has already been provided, i.e.
          the user is using the Install from Web feature. If, however, the
          user has not used the Install from Web feature the Stream ID above
          generates a download URL identical to the one of the stream_link
          syntax above.</para>

          <para>Yes, we understand this is confusing. You know what is more
          confusing? Trying to figure out how the Install from Web feature
          works based on useless documentation and convoluted code, but we
          digress.</para>

          <para>Please note that this is the URL, not a link! If you want to
          use it as a link you will need something like this:</para>

          <para><programlisting>&lt;a href="{arslatest installfromweb 123}"&gt;Install or download latest version&lt;/a&gt;</programlisting>or
          combine it with the version number syntax to have something even
          more useful:</para>

          <para><programlisting>&lt;a href="{arslatest installfromweb 123}"&gt;Install or download
Foobar version {arslatest release Foobar}&lt;/a&gt;</programlisting></para>

          <tip>
            <para>You can use this feature in your successful login /
            subscription message page to let the user install / download your
            software.</para>
          </tip>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="bleedingedge-repositories">
        <title>How the BleedingEdge categories work</title>

        <para>BleedingEdge (BE) categories are quite different than the
        Normal-type categories. You don't have to visit your site's back-end
        to publish and unpublish releases and items. It all happens
        automatically whenever you upload or delete files on your server. Here
        is the breakdown of how that works.</para>

        <para>As all ARS categories, BleedingEdge categories are linked with a
        Files Directory. Unlike Normal-type categories, BE categories
        continuously monitor that directory for changes. Whenever you create a
        new subdirectory, a new ARS Release is created. The Version of the ARS
        Release is the directory's name and its Maturity is always set to
        "Alpha". Here is the coolness factor for software releases: If you
        upload a plain text file named CHANGELOG (yes, all caps and no
        extension), ARS will read it, compare it with the previous releases's
        CHANGELOG, colorize the result and use that as the ARS Release's
        description. The colorizer follows the Joomla! standard on marking
        changes in the CHANGELOG:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Lines starting with # (hash) indicate bug fixes</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Lines starting with + (plus) indicate added features</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Lines starting with - (dash) indicate removed
            features</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Lines starting with ~ (tilde) indicate miscellaneous
            changes</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>All other lines are comments and/or notes</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>If you're not interested in colorizing, changelogs and stuff
        like that, just keep in mind that if you upload a plain text file
        named CHANGELOG it will be used as your ARS Release's
        description.</para>

        <para>Finally, for each file you upload an item be created and
        published. If you have set up Automatic Item Descriptions for the
        category they will, of course, be used for naming the file. ARS
        Releases and ARS Items created this way will inherit the access (view)
        level and AMBRA Group settings of the BE category.</para>

        <para>Let's sum it up, OK?</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Creating directories creates releases</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A text file named CHANGELOG will be used to produce your
            release's description</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Uploading files creates items</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Access (view) levels and AMBRA Group settings are inherited
            from the category to the release, to the items</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Deleting a directory unpublishes the release</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Deleting a file unpublishes the item</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>You don't need to login to your back-end to manage the
            releases and items, but if you want to, you can.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="updating-maxmind-geoip">
        <title>Updating the MaxMind GeoLite2 Country (GeoIP) database</title>

        <note>
          <para>This product includes GeoLite2 data created by MaxMind,
          available from <link xlink:href="http://www.maxmind.com"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">MaxMind</link>.</para>
        </note>

        <bridgehead>What is the GeoIP database, installing and updating
        it</bridgehead>

        <para>Logging the country of origin of a download in Akeeba Release
        System requires it to be able to find out the country and / or
        continent associated with the IP address of a visitor of your site.
        Naturally, IPs do not carry geographic information so we need an
        external database which has this kind of information.</para>

        <para>Akeeba Release System requires you to install an optional plugin
        called "System - Akeeba GeoIP provider plugin". You can download it
        for free <link
        xlink:href="https://www.akeebabackup.com/download/akgeoip.html"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">from our site</link>.
        Please remember to enable it after you install it.</para>

        <para>This plugin is using the third party MaxMind GeoLite2 database
        to match IPs to countries and continents. This list is not static,
        i.e. it is updated about once per month. Admin Tools can attempt to
        download its newest version by clicking the <guibutton>Update the
        GeoLite2 Country database</guibutton> button in the Control Panel
        page. However, if this is not possible (for reasons ranging from your
        host restrictions to permissions issues) you can do so
        manually.</para>

        <para
        xlink:href="http://geolite.maxmind.com/download/geoip/database/GeoLite2-Country.mmdb.gz"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">You can download the latest
        version of <link
        xlink:href="http://dev.maxmind.com/geoip/geoip2/geolite2/">MaxMing
        GeoLite2 database</link> in binary format, from <link
        xlink:href="???">http://geolite.maxmind.com/download/geoip/database/GeoLite2-Country.mmdb.gz</link>.
        Extract the downloaded compressed file using gunzip on Linux, 7-Zip on
        Windows or BetterZIP on Mac OS X. It will result in a file named
        <filename>GeoLite2-Country.mmdb.gz</filename>. Upload it to your
        site's <filename>plugins/system/akgeoip/db</filename> directory
        overwriting the existing file.</para>

        <important>
          <para>Capitalization matters! You have to upload the file as
          <filename>GeoLite2-Country.mmdb.gz</filename>, not
          <filename>geolite2-country.mmdb.gz</filename> or any other
          combination of lowercase / capital letters, otherwise IT WILL NOT
          WORK, AT ALL.</para>
        </important>

        <tip>
          <para>If you are a subscriber to MaxMind's more accurate (99.8%
          advertised accuracy), for-a-fee GeoIP Country database you can use
          that database instead of the free GeoLite2 database included in the
          component, using the same procedure.</para>
        </tip>

        <para>Do note that download log records prior to installing the new
        version of the database will not be affected. Only download attempts
        logged after uploading the new database version will be affected by
        the new database version.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="cli-update-script">
        <title>The CLI update notification and automatic update script</title>

        <note>
          <para>This feature is only available in the Professional
          release.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Since March 2014 all of our software uses Joomla! Extensions
        Update to determine if there is an extension available and to let you
        install it. None of our own code is involved in the update
        provisioning and installation process. However, this means that you
        need to either log in to your site often to see if there are updates
        available or subscribe to a third party service which will do that for
        you. The former is inconvenient when you have multiple sites, the
        latter is expensive.</para>

        <para>This is where our CLI update script come into the big picture.
        This script will ask Joomla! to tell it if there is an update
        available for our component. If there is, it can do either (or both)
        of these actions:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Send an email notification to the email address you have
            specified.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Ask Joomla! to install the available update
            automatically.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <warning>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">AUTOMATIC INSTALLATION OF UPDATES IS A
          VERY BAD IDEA AND CAN LEAD TO YOUR SITE BECOMING
          INACCESSIBLE!</emphasis> Read below for more information. Akeeba Ltd
          does not accept any responsibility for any problems, data loss or
          other side effects which might arise directly or indirectly from the
          use, misuse or abuse of our software per the license of the
          software. Since the actual update code is part of Joomla! itself (it
          is not written by us) we cannot provide bug fixes, making the use of
          this script exempt from our support policy. IF YOU DECIDE TO USE
          THIS SCRIPT TO INSTALL UPDATES OF OUR SOFTWARE AUTOMATICALLY YOU ARE
          DOING SO AT YOUR OWN RISK.</para>
        </warning>

        <para>Joomla! currently does not provide a way to indicate the
        stability status (alpha, beta, RC, stable), Joomla! version
        compatibility and PHP version compatibility status of an available
        update. This means that in the future you might end up having the
        automatic update CLI script install a version of our software which is
        unstable or incompatible with your version of PHP or Joomla!. We
        strongly recommend you to check the Compatibility page on our site to
        determine which version is compatible with your site.</para>

        <para>Furthermore, Joomla! does not provide a rollback feature for
        failed updates. If for any reason the update process (which is handled
        by Joomla! itself, not our own code, therefore outside our control)
        fails while it is copying the component's files you will end up with a
        partially upgrade component. This can lead to functional issues or
        even inability to access your site.</para>

        <para>Finally, even if you have Akeeba Backup Professional, System
        Restore Points CAN NOT be taken when installing an update through the
        CLI update script. If the update fails you are really left with no
        backup.</para>

        <bridgehead renderas="sect2">Configuring the update
        script</bridgehead>

        <para>The update script can be configured from the Options page of the
        component. Please go to the component's main (control panel) page and
        click on the <guibutton>Options</guibutton> button. On the new page,
        click on the <guilabel>Live Update</guilabel> tab. You have the
        following options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Auto-update CLI settings</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>What you want the update CLI to do when Joomla! reports
              that a new version is available.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Notify and update</guilabel>. It will send
                  you an email to notify you about the available update and
                  immediately ask Joomla! to install it.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Notify only</guilabel>. RECOMMENDED. It will
                  only send you an email to notify you about the available
                  update.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para><guilabel>Update only</guilabel>. Not recommended! It
                  will only ask Joomla! to install the available update,
                  without any further notification.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Notification frequency</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The <emphasis>maximum</emphasis> frequency you will be
              receiving update notification emails if you use the "Notify and
              update" or "Notify only" options above. This field only contains
              a number, by default it's 1. Please look at the next option
              too.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Notification time</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The time period expressed by notification frequency. For
              example, if you set the notification frequency to 1 and the
              notification time to "days" you will receive update notification
              emails for the new version <emphasis>at most</emphasis> once a
              day.</para>

              <important>
                <para>These two options only define the
                <emphasis>maximum</emphasis> update notification frequency.
                You may receive update emails <emphasis>less
                frequently</emphasis> than what you have set up. It depends on
                how often then CLI update script runs and how often Joomla!
                performs the update check. It is always possible that you will
                not be notified about an update which has been released in the
                last two days because Joomla! hasn't yet "seen" it.</para>
              </important>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Email for update notifications</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The email address where update notification emails will be
              sent. If you do not specify an address no update notification
              email will be sent. You can only specify a singe email
              address.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <bridgehead renderas="sect2">Creating a CRON job for the update
        script</bridgehead>

        <para>You can only use this feature if you have access to the
        command-line version of PHP. In order to schedule an automatic update,
        you will have to use the following command line to your host's CRON
        interface:</para>

        <programlisting><replaceable>/usr/local/bin/php</replaceable> <replaceable>/home/USER/webroot</replaceable>/cli/ars-update.php</programlisting>

        <para>where <replaceable>/usr/local/bin/php</replaceable> is the path
        to your PHP CLI executable and
        <replaceable>/home/USER/webroot</replaceable> is the absolute path to
        your web site's root. You can get this information from your
        host.</para>

        <para>The update script does not accept any parameters.</para>

        <para>In order to give you an example, we will assume that your PHP
        CLI binary is located in <filename>/usr/local/bin/php</filename> - a
        common setting among hosts - and that your web site's root is located
        at <filename>/home/johndoe/httpdocs</filename> :</para>

        <programlisting>usr/local/bin/php /home/johndoe/httpdocs/cli/ars-update.php</programlisting>

        <para>Special considerations:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Most hosts do not impose a time limit on scripts running
            from the command-line. If your host does and the limit is less
            than the required time to send an update notification and/or
            install the update your site, the update will fail.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>This script is not meant to run from a web interface. If
            your host only provides access to the CGI or FastCGI PHP binaries
            the script may not work with them. The reason is the time
            constraint explained above.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Some servers do not fully support this update method. The
            usual symptoms will be an update which fails to complete without
            any further error messages and no indication of something going
            wrong. In such a case, trying to ryn the update from the back-end
            of your site will work properly.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <bridgehead>Setting up a CRON job on cPanel</bridgehead>

        <para>Go to your cPanel main page and choose the <guibutton>CRON
        Jobs</guibutton> icon from the <guilabel>Advanced</guilabel> pane. In
        the <guilabel>Add New CRON Job</guilabel> box on the page which loads,
        enter the following information:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Common Settings</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Choose the frequency of your backup, for example once per
              day.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Command</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Enter your backup command. Usually, you have to use
              something like:</para>

              <programlisting>/usr/bin/php5-cli /home/<replaceable>myusername</replaceable>/public_html/cli/ars-update.php</programlisting>

              <para>where <replaceable>myusername</replaceable> is your
              account's user name (most probably the same you use to login to
              cPanel). Do note the path for the PHP command line executable:
              <filename>/usr/bin/php5-cli</filename>. This is the default
              location of the correct executable file for cPanel 11 and later.
              Your host may use a different path to the executable. If the
              command never runs, ask them. We can't help you with that; only
              those who have set up the server know the changes they have made
              to the default setup.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>Finally, click the <guibutton>Add New Cron Job</guibutton>
        button to activate the CRON job.</para>

        <bridgehead>Special considerations for HostGator</bridgehead>

        <para>The location of the PHP CLI binary is
        <filename>/usr/bin/php-cli</filename>. This means that your CRON
        command line should look like:</para>

        <para><programlisting>/opt/php53/bin/php /home/<replaceable>myusername</replaceable>/public_html/cli/ars-update.php</programlisting></para>
      </section>
    </chapter>
  </part>

  <part xml:id="appendices">
    <title>Appendices</title>

    <appendix version="5.0" xml:id="gnu-fdl">
      <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>

      <para>Copyright (C) 2000, 2001, 2002 Free Software Foundation,
      <abbrev>Inc.</abbrev> 51 Franklin <abbrev>St</abbrev> , Fifth Floor,
      Boston, <abbrev>MA</abbrev> 02110-1301 <abbrev
      role="initialism">USA</abbrev> . Everyone is permitted to copy and
      distribute verbatim copies of this license document, but changing it is
      not allowed.</para>

      <bridgehead renderas="sect1">0. PREAMBLE</bridgehead>

      <para>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or
      other functional and useful document "free" in the sense of freedom: to
      assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it, with
      or without modifying it, either commercially or noncommercially.
      Secondarily, this License preserves for the author and publisher a way
      to get credit for their work, while not being considered responsible for
      modifications made by others.</para>

      <para>This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that derivative
      works of the document must themselves be free in the same sense. It
      complements the GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft license
      designed for free software.</para>

      <para>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for
      free software, because free software needs free documentation: a free
      program should come with manuals providing the same freedoms that the
      software does. But this License is not limited to software manuals; it
      can be used for any textual work, regardless of subject matter or
      whether it is published as a printed book. We recommend this License
      principally for works whose purpose is instruction or reference.</para>

      <bridgehead renderas="sect1">1. APPLICABILITY AND
      DEFINITIONS</bridgehead>

      <para>This License applies to any manual or other work, in any medium,
      that contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
      distributed under the terms of this License. Such a notice grants a
      world-wide, royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use that
      work under the conditions stated herein. The "Document", below, refers
      to any such manual or work. Any member of the public is a licensee, and
      is addressed as "you". You accept the license if you copy, modify or
      distribute the work in a way requiring permission under copyright
      law.</para>

      <para>A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work containing the
      Document or a portion of it, either copied verbatim, or with
      modifications and/or translated into another language.</para>

      <para>A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter
      section of the Document that deals exclusively with the relationship of
      the publishers or authors of the Document to the Document's overall
      subject (or to related matters) and contains nothing that could fall
      directly within that overall subject. (Thus, if the Document is in part
      a textbook of mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any
      mathematics.) The relationship could be a matter of historical
      connection with the subject or with related matters, or of legal,
      commercial, philosophical, ethical or political position regarding
      them.</para>

      <para>The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections whose
      titles are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the
      notice that says that the Document is released under this License. If a
      section does not fit the above definition of Secondary then it is not
      allowed to be designated as Invariant. The Document may contain zero
      Invariant Sections. If the Document does not identify any Invariant
      Sections then there are none.</para>

      <para>The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that are
      listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the notice that
      says that the Document is released under this License. A Front-Cover
      Text may be at most 5 words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at most 25
      words.</para>

      <para>A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a machine-readable
      copy, represented in a format whose specification is available to the
      general public, that is suitable for revising the document
      straightforwardly with generic text editors or (for images composed of
      pixels) generic paint programs or (for drawings) some widely available
      drawing editor, and that is suitable for input to text formatters or for
      automatic translation to a variety of formats suitable for input to text
      formatters. A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file format whose
      markup, or absence of markup, has been arranged to thwart or discourage
      subsequent modification by readers is not Transparent. An image format
      is not Transparent if used for any substantial amount of text. A copy
      that is not "Transparent" is called "Opaque".</para>

      <para>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain
      ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML or
      XML using a publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple HTML,
      PostScript or PDF designed for human modification. Examples of
      transparent image formats include PNG, XCF and JPG. Opaque formats
      include proprietary formats that can be read and edited only by
      proprietary word processors, SGML or XML for which the DTD and/or
      processing tools are not generally available, and the machine-generated
      HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by some word processors for output
      purposes only.</para>

      <para>The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page itself,
      plus such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly, the material
      this License requires to appear in the title page. For works in formats
      which do not have any title page as such, "Title Page" means the text
      near the most prominent appearance of the work's title, preceding the
      beginning of the body of the text.</para>

      <para>A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named subunit of the Document
      whose title either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in parentheses
      following text that translates XYZ in another language. (Here XYZ stands
      for a specific section name mentioned below, such as "Acknowledgements",
      "Dedications", "Endorsements", or "History".) To "Preserve the Title" of
      such a section when you modify the Document means that it remains a
      section "Entitled XYZ" according to this definition.</para>

      <para>The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice
      which states that this License applies to the Document. These Warranty
      Disclaimers are considered to be included by reference in this License,
      but only as regards disclaiming warranties: any other implication that
      these Warranty Disclaimers may have is void and has no effect on the
      meaning of this License.</para>

      <bridgehead renderas="sect1">2. VERBATIM COPYING</bridgehead>

      <para>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either
      commercially or noncommercially, provided that this License, the
      copyright notices, and the license notice saying this License applies to
      the Document are reproduced in all copies, and that you add no other
      conditions whatsoever to those of this License. You may not use
      technical measures to obstruct or control the reading or further copying
      of the copies you make or distribute. However, you may accept
      compensation in exchange for copies. If you distribute a large enough
      number of copies you must also follow the conditions in section
      3.</para>

      <para>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above,
      and you may publicly display copies.</para>

      <bridgehead renderas="sect1">3. COPYING IN QUANTITY</bridgehead>

      <para>If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly
      have printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the
      Document's license notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the
      copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover Texts:
      Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back
      cover. Both covers must also clearly and legibly identify you as the
      publisher of these copies. The front cover must present the full title
      with all words of the title equally prominent and visible. You may add
      other material on the covers in addition. Copying with changes limited
      to the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the Document and
      satisfy these conditions, can be treated as verbatim copying in other
      respects.</para>

      <para>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit
      legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit
      reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent
      pages.</para>

      <para>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document
      numbering more than 100, you must either include a machine-readable
      Transparent copy along with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each
      Opaque copy a computer-network location from which the general
      network-using public has access to download using public-standard
      network protocols a complete Transparent copy of the Document, free of
      added material. If you use the latter option, you must take reasonably
      prudent steps, when you begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity,
      to ensure that this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the
      stated location until at least one year after the last time you
      distribute an Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or retailers)
      of that edition to the public.</para>

      <para>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors of
      the Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to
      give them a chance to provide you with an updated version of the
      Document.</para>

      <bridgehead renderas="sect1">4. MODIFICATIONS</bridgehead>

      <para>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document
      under the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you
      release the Modified Version under precisely this License, with the
      Modified Version filling the role of the Document, thus licensing
      distribution and modification of the Modified Version to whoever
      possesses a copy of it. In addition, you must do these things in the
      Modified Version:</para>

      <orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a title
          distinct from that of the Document, and from those of previous
          versions (which should, if there were any, be listed in the History
          section of the Document). You may use the same title as a previous
          version if the original publisher of that version gives
          permission.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more persons or
          entities responsible for authorship of the modifications in the
          Modified Version, together with at least five of the principal
          authors of the Document (all of its principal authors, if it has
          fewer than five), unless they release you from this
          requirement.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>State on the Title page the name of the publisher of the
          Modified Version, as the publisher.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve all the copyright notices of the
          Document.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications
          adjacent to the other copyright notices.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a license
          notice giving the public permission to use the Modified Version
          under the terms of this License, in the form shown in the Addendum
          below.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant
          Sections and required Cover Texts given in the Document's license
          notice.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Include an unaltered copy of this License.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve its
          Title, and add to it an item stating at least the title, year, new
          authors, and publisher of the Modified Version as given on the Title
          Page. If there is no section Entitled "History" in the Document,
          create one stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the
          Document as given on its Title Page, then add an item describing the
          Modified Version as stated in the previous sentence.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve the network location, if any, given in the
          Document for public access to a Transparent copy of the Document,
          and likewise the network locations given in the Document for
          previous versions it was based on. These may be placed in the
          "History" section. You may omit a network location for a work that
          was published at least four years before the Document itself, or if
          the original publisher of the version it refers to gives
          permission.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>For any section Entitled "Acknowledgements" or
          "Dedications", Preserve the Title of the section, and preserve in
          the section all the substance and tone of each of the contributor
          acknowledgements and/or dedications given therein.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document,
          unaltered in their text and in their titles. Section numbers or the
          equivalent are not considered part of the section titles.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements". Such a section
          may not be included in the Modified Version.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled
          "Endorsements" or to conflict in title with any Invariant
          Section.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.</simpara>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or
      appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material
      copied from the Document, you may at your option designate some or all
      of these sections as invariant. To do this, add their titles to the list
      of Invariant Sections in the Modified Version's license notice. These
      titles must be distinct from any other section titles.</para>

      <para>You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it
      contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various
      parties--for example, statements of peer review or that the text has
      been approved by an organization as the authoritative definition of a
      standard.</para>

      <para>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text,
      and a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the
      list of Cover Texts in the Modified Version. Only one passage of
      Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or through
      arrangements made by) any one entity. If the Document already includes a
      cover text for the same cover, previously added by you or by arrangement
      made by the same entity you are acting on behalf of, you may not add
      another; but you may replace the old one, on explicit permission from
      the previous publisher that added the old one.</para>

      <para>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this
      License give permission to use their names for publicity for or to
      assert or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</para>

      <bridgehead renderas="sect1">5. COMBINING DOCUMENTS</bridgehead>

      <para>You may combine the Document with other documents released under
      this License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for modified
      versions, provided that you include in the combination all of the
      Invariant Sections of all of the original documents, unmodified, and
      list them all as Invariant Sections of your combined work in its license
      notice, and that you preserve all their Warranty Disclaimers.</para>

      <para>The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and
      multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single
      copy. If there are multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but
      different contents, make the title of each such section unique by adding
      at the end of it, in parentheses, the name of the original author or
      publisher of that section if known, or else a unique number. Make the
      same adjustment to the section titles in the list of Invariant Sections
      in the license notice of the combined work.</para>

      <para>In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled
      "History" in the various original documents, forming one section
      Entitled "History"; likewise combine any sections Entitled
      "Acknowledgements", and any sections Entitled "Dedications". You must
      delete all sections Entitled "Endorsements".</para>

      <bridgehead renderas="sect1">6. COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</bridgehead>

      <para>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other
      documents released under this License, and replace the individual copies
      of this License in the various documents with a single copy that is
      included in the collection, provided that you follow the rules of this
      License for verbatim copying of each of the documents in all other
      respects.</para>

      <para>You may extract a single document from such a collection, and
      distribute it individually under this License, provided you insert a
      copy of this License into the extracted document, and follow this
      License in all other respects regarding verbatim copying of that
      document.</para>

      <bridgehead renderas="sect1">7. AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT
      WORKS</bridgehead>

      <para>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other
      separate and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a
      storage or distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the
      copyright resulting from the compilation is not used to limit the legal
      rights of the compilation's users beyond what the individual works
      permit. When the Document is included in an aggregate, this License does
      not apply to the other works in the aggregate which are not themselves
      derivative works of the Document.</para>

      <para>If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to these
      copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of
      the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may be placed on covers
      that bracket the Document within the aggregate, or the electronic
      equivalent of covers if the Document is in electronic form. Otherwise
      they must appear on printed covers that bracket the whole
      aggregate.</para>

      <bridgehead renderas="sect1">8. TRANSLATION</bridgehead>

      <para>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
      distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section 4.
      Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires special
      permission from their copyright holders, but you may include
      translations of some or all Invariant Sections in addition to the
      original versions of these Invariant Sections. You may include a
      translation of this License, and all the license notices in the
      Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers, provided that you also include
      the original English version of this License and the original versions
      of those notices and disclaimers. In case of a disagreement between the
      translation and the original version of this License or a notice or
      disclaimer, the original version will prevail.</para>

      <para>If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgements",
      "Dedications", or "History", the requirement (section 4) to Preserve its
      Title (section 1) will typically require changing the actual
      title.</para>

      <bridgehead renderas="sect1">9. TERMINATION</bridgehead>

      <para>You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document
      except as expressly provided for under this License. Any other attempt
      to copy, modify, sublicense or distribute the Document is void, and will
      automatically terminate your rights under this License. However, parties
      who have received copies, or rights, from you under this License will
      not have their licenses terminated so long as such parties remain in
      full compliance.</para>

      <bridgehead renderas="sect1">10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS
      LICENSE</bridgehead>

      <para>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions of
      the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new versions
      will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ in
      detail to address new problems or concerns. See <link
      xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/</link> .</para>

      <para>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version
      number. If the Document specifies that a particular numbered version of
      this License "or any later version" applies to it, you have the option
      of following the terms and conditions either of that specified version
      or of any later version that has been published (not as a draft) by the
      Free Software Foundation. If the Document does not specify a version
      number of this License, you may choose any version ever published (not
      as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation.</para>

      <bridgehead renderas="sect1">ADDENDUM: How to use this License for your
      documents</bridgehead>

      <para>To use this License in a document you have written, include a copy
      of the License in the document and put the following copyright and
      license notices just after the title page:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para>Copyright (C) YEAR YOUR NAME.</para>

        <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
        document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License,
        Version 1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software
        Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no
        Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section
        entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".</para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and Back-Cover
      Texts, replace the "with...Texts." line with this:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para>with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the
        Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being
        LIST.</para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some other
      combination of the three, merge those two alternatives to suit the
      situation.</para>

      <para>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code, we
      recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your choice of free
      software license, such as the GNU General Public License, to permit
      their use in free software.</para>
    </appendix>
  </part>
</book>
